{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This modern-day country was outraged by the Council of Blood being imposed as its ruler, as\nwell as by the Tenth Penny tax. It allied with the \"Sea Beggars\" against Spanish governors such\nas the Duke of Alba and won its independence in the Eighty Years War. For 10 points, name this\ncountry where William the Silent reigned over land reclaimed from the sea via dikes.",
      "answer": [
        "the Netherlands",
        "Holland",
        "the United Provinces"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This woman was implicated in a fraud known as the Affair of the Diamond Necklace. She\nbecame known as \"the widow Capet\" following the death of her husband, Louis XVI. For 10\npoints, name this queen of France who legendarily dismissed a crowd of peasants crying out for\nbread by saying \"let them eat cake.\"",
      "answer": "Marie Antoinette"
    },
    {
      "question": "These people believed that people who died by drowning went to an underworld ruled by\nTlaloc (pr. tuh-LAH-lock) rather than the main underworld, Mictlan (pr. MIKT-lon). These\npeople believed that an eagle with a snake in its mouth had alighted on a cactus, telling them\nwhere to build their capital. For 10 points, name this group that worshipped Quetzalcoatl (pr.\nKET-sul-coh-AH-tul).",
      "answer": [
        "Aztecs",
        "Aztec"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A sculpture group by this artist depicts an incident in which Eustache de Saint Pierre led six\nmen into captivity in 1347 following a battle with Edward III. The most iconic piece by this\nsculptor was part of his exhibition The Gates of Hell and represents Dante planning the Divine\nComedy. For 10 points, name this sculptor of The Burghers of Calais and The Thinker.",
      "answer": [
        "Auguste Rodin",
        "Rodin"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This industry became involved in a scandal during the Spanish-American War when it\nsupplied poor-quality goods to Nelson Miles's troops in Puerto Rico. This industry was later\nfictionalized as mistreating immigrant Jurgis Rudkus, leading Theodore Roosevelt to support the\nPure Food and Drug Act. For 10 points, name this industry which Upton Sinclair targeted in The\nJungle.",
      "answer": [
        "meatpacking industry",
        "meat"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Two sports teams based in this country met in the Naismith Cup. In 1993, a team based in this\ncountry employed John Olerud and Paul Molitor. This country's lesser-known national sport is\nlacrosse, and its football league contests the Grey Cup every year. For 10 points, name this\nformer home of the NBA's Grizzlies and current home of baseball's Blue Jays.",
      "answer": "Canada"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man personally financed and organized a rescue mission for employees of Electronic\nData Systems who were imprisoned in Iran. He chose James Stockdale as his running mate in a\nPresidential election that saw him widely mocked for buying network airtime to display a series\nof charts. For 10 points, name this independent who received twenty percent of the vote in 1992.",
      "answer": [
        "H. Ross Perot",
        "Perot",
        "Hiriam Ross Perot"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Emmanuel Timoni first described a method of preventing this disease, which Mary Worley\nMontagu famously was guarded against in Constantinople. Cotton Mather wrote in support of\ninoculation against this disease, which was proved feasible in England by Edward Jenner. For 10\npoints, name this formerly devastating disease which was eliminated by the 1990s.",
      "answer": "smallpox"
    },
    {
      "question": "The chief justice during this event, William Stoughton, controversially allowed \"spectral\nevidence\" to be introduced, an action later condemned by Increase Mather. These events began\nwith accusations against the slave Tituba and resulted in dozens of executions by hanging and\npressing. For 10 points, name this episode of mass hysteria in 1692 Massachusetts.",
      "answer": "Salem witch trials"
    },
    {
      "question": "Much of the groundwork for this institution was laid at the San Francisco Conference by spy\nAlger Hiss. At this institution, Valerian Zorin was told “don’t wait for the translation” by Adlai\nStevenson, who served as U.S. ambassador to this institution under John F. Kennedy. For 10\npoints, name this successor to the League of Nations which meets in New York.",
      "answer": [
        "the UN",
        "United Nations"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "(TIEBREAKER EXAMPLE QUESTION) The Qing Dynasty was founded by what ethnic group from the north of China, which\nmandated that all Han Chinese wear their hair in queues?",
      "answer": [
        "Manchus",
        "Manchu",
        "Manchurians",
        "Manchurian"
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "When setting up skeletons of this species for display, museums frequently used the skull of\nCamarasaurus. That practice perpetuated Othniel Charles Marsh's belief that this species was not\nidentical to a skeleton unearthed in 1885. For 10 points, identify this dinosaur species which\nMarsh erroneously identified as separate from the fictitious \"brontosaurus.\"",
        "answer": "apatosaurus"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The apatosaurus flourished during what middle period of the Mesozoic era?",
        "answer": [
          "Jurassic Period",
          "Jurassic"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man hid out at Liliesleaf Farm after the Treason Trial, where he organized the militant\ngroup Spear of the Nation. He gave the \"I Am Prepared to Die\" speech at the Rivonia Trial,\nwhich led to his lengthy imprisonment on Robben Island. For 10 points, name this man who\nultimately worked with F.W. de Klerk to end the apartheid system in South Africa.",
        "answer": [
          "Nelson Rolihlahla Mandela",
          "Mandela",
          "Nelson Mandela"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Mandela's Spear of the Nation was the paramilitary wing of what anti-apartheid group,\nwhich has been the governing political party of South Africa since 1994?",
        "answer": [
          "ANC",
          "African National Congress"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Jacob Bernoulli discovered that this number is the \"force of interest,\" the limit of the interest\naccruable on a dollar by increasing the frequency of compounding. A 1727 paper on the\nexplosive force of cannons introduced this number as the base of the natural logarithm. For 10\npoints, identify this mathematical constant named for its Swiss popularizer.",
        "answer": [
          "e",
          "Euler's number",
          "Euler's constant"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Euler (pr. OY-ler) also established graph theory in an attempt to solve the problem\ninvolving seven of what kind of structure in Königsberg?",
        "answer": [
          "bridges",
          "bridge"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This composer incorporated \"Springfield Mountain\" and \"Camptown Races,\" along with\nexcerpts from the Gettysburg Address, into his World War II patriotic piece A Lincoln Portrait.\nHe scored ballets about Billy the Kid and about pioneers building a farmhouse in western\nPennsylvania. For 10 points, name this composer of Appalachian Spring.",
        "answer": [
          "Aaron Copland",
          "Copland"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "As part of the same biographical project that led Copland to create A Lincoln Portrait,\nVirgil Thomson set poems by what author of Leaves of Grass?",
        "answer": [
          "Walt Whitman",
          "Whitman",
          "Walter Whitman"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This device was originally named for doctor Antoine Louis. The \"tricoteuse\" (pr. TRICK-awtooz) were women who knitted next to this object. This object was used on up to forty thousand\npeople at the order of Maximilien Robespierre, who found himself subject to it in 1794. For 10\npoints, name this item which was used to execute Louis XVI and others during the French\nRevolution.",
        "answer": "guillotine"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The guillotine was originally used to equalize execution methods for nobles and\nmembers of what group, the peasant section of France in the Estates-General?",
        "answer": [
          "Third Estate",
          "Third"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This system was restored following the overthrow of Hippias (pr. HIP-ee-uss), after which its\ncentral feature was the boulé (pr. BOO-lay). This system involved citizens being arranged into\ndemes (pr. DEEMZ) by Cleisthenes (pr. CLICE-thuh-neez). For 10 points, identify this\npolitical system used in classical Athens, which inspired similar vote-based systems in the\nmodern world.",
        "answer": [
          "Athenian democracy",
          "democracy"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Members of the boulé were selected by what method, also used to pick the tenth of an\narmy that Romans \"decimated\" and the date of the massacre of Jews in the Book of Esther?",
        "answer": [
          "by drawing of lots",
          "lot",
          "lots"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This language was used to write The Incoherence of the Philosophers, which was rebutted\nwith The Incoherence of the Incoherence. This was the language used by the medieval\nphilosopher Averroes (pr. AA-vuh-ROE-ez) and other writers based at Córdoba (pr. COREdoh-buh). For 10 points, name this language through which many Greek and Latin texts passed\nto Europe.",
        "answer": "Arabic"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Which other Semitic language, which was the language which Jesus spoke, was\nfeatured in the Mel Gibson directed film, The Passion of the Christ?",
        "answer": "Aramaic"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In the twentieth century, some groups modified this holiday to use a \"cup of Miriam\" to\nsymbolize women and an orange to symbolize homosexuals. This holiday also changed in the\ntwelfth century, when its service was collected as the \"haggadah\" (pr. hah-GUH-duh). For 10\npoints, name this Jewish holiday on which the \"seder\" (pr. SAY-dur) meal includes matzah\n(MAHT-suh).",
        "answer": [
          "Passover",
          "Pesach"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What book of the Bible, in which Moses leads the Jews out of Egypt, is the focus of\nPassover?",
        "answer": [
          "Book of Exodus",
          "Exodus",
          "Sh'mot"
        ]
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "THE CARIBBEAN",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "In the history of the Caribbean islands, who or what was the…\nStyle of music originating in Trinidad practiced by Harry Belafonte (pr. beh-luh-FON-tay)\nand Lord Invader?",
          "answer": "calypso"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country that colonized Martinique (pr. mar-tin-EEK), Guadeloupe (pr. gwah-duh-LOOP),\nand Haiti?",
          "answer": "France"
        },
        {
          "question": "Group including St. Croix (pr. CROY), St. John, and St. Thomas that has U.S. and British\nsections?",
          "answer": "Virgin Islands"
        },
        {
          "question": "Crop harvested under the “gang system” in the most harsh form of slavery?",
          "answer": "sugar"
        },
        {
          "question": "Regiment led by Leonard Wood and Theodore Roosevelt that captured San Juan Hill?",
          "answer": [
            "Rough Riders",
            "1st United States Volunteer Cavalry",
            "1st Cavalry"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Island where Maurice Bishop's execution led to the American Operation Urgent Fury in 1983?",
          "answer": "Grenada"
        },
        {
          "question": "British colony where the Maroon Wars involving escaped slaves took place?",
          "answer": "Jamaica"
        },
        {
          "question": "Dominican dictator assassinated with American approval in 1961?",
          "answer": [
            "Rafael Trujillo",
            "Trujillo"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "EMANCIPATION OF SERFS",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "The emancipation of the world's largest serf population…\nOccurred in what empire, which was ultimately ended by the deposition of Tsar Nicholas II?",
          "answer": [
            "Russian Empire",
            "Russia"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Began in what year, also the year Abraham Lincoln's Presidency and the Civil War started?",
          "answer": "1861"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was instigated by what tsar, who was assassinated twenty years later?",
          "answer": "Alexander II"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ended the landlord veto over serfs engaging in what practice, the subject of the American\ncourt case Loving v. Virginia?",
          "answer": [
            "marriage",
            "weddings",
            "wedding"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was part of the fallout from Russia's defeat by Britain, France, and Turkey in what war?",
          "answer": [
            "Crimean War",
            "Crimean"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Led radicals to support what political position that characterized the Nechaevists, Land and\nLiberty, and The People's Will?",
          "answer": [
            "anarchism",
            "nihilism"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Set up what system of elected provincial councils?",
          "answer": [
            "zemstvos",
            "zemstvo"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Required that former serfs do what for forty-nine years?",
          "answer": [
            "submit redemption payments to former owners",
            "redemption payment"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "EARLY PHILADELPHIA",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "The American city of Philadelphia was…\nThe initial capital of what colony, set up as a religious refuge?",
          "answer": "Pennsylvania"
        },
        {
          "question": "The place where what document, written by Thomas Jefferson, was signed in July 1776?",
          "answer": "Declaration of Independence"
        },
        {
          "question": "Where what kite-flying inventor of bifocals published the Gazette?",
          "answer": [
            "Benjamin Franklin",
            "Franklin"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Where the first American instance of what kind of institution, which now includes New York\nPresbyterian and Cedars-Sinai, was established?",
          "answer": "hospital"
        },
        {
          "question": "Named for the “brotherly love” exhibited by what pacifist Christian sect?",
          "answer": [
            "Quakers",
            "Quaker",
            "Religious Society of Friends",
            "Friends"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Lost to the British in September 1777 following Howe's defeat of Washington at what creek?",
          "answer": [
            "Battle of Brandywine Creek",
            "Brandywine"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The site of a 1793 epidemic of what disease, which Walter Reed combatted at the Panama\nCanal?",
          "answer": "yellow fever"
        },
        {
          "question": "Where what cartoon, featuring an eight-segmented snake, was published in 1754?",
          "answer": "Join or Die"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Letters leaked by Henry Simpson McComb first exposed this company's actions to the\nNew York Sun. This company was organized by George Train and Thomas (20 pts) ",
        "Durant, and\nit began a cozy relationship with Congress following the installation of Oakes (10 pts) ",
        "Ames as\nits president. It held an inflated contract with the Union Pacific railroad. For 10 points, name this\ncompany at the center of an 1872 Grant administration scandal involving political graft."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Credit Mobilier of America",
        "Credit Mobilier"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A succession war named for this area began on the death of Maximilian Joseph in 1777\nand was also known as the \"potato war.\" Motifs from Wagner (pr. VOG-ner) operas are\nused to decorate the (20 pts) ",
        "Neuschwanstein (pr. noy-SHVON-shtine) Castle in this region,\nwhich was built by its (10 pts) ",
        "\"Mad\" king Ludwig II. For 10 points, name this southeastern German\nstate and historic kingdom, where many German Catholics and the city of Munich can be found."
      ],
      "answer": "Bavaria"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The protagonist of this TV show insisted that if Ronald Reagan dyed his hair, he only did\nso \"to show his strength to the Communists,\" and had his faith in the Republican Party\ntested when he discovered that (20 pts) ",
        "George W. Bush had a limp handshake. An episode of\nthis show is about a plot to steal Santa Anna's (10 pts) ",
        "wooden leg on its way back to Mexico, and\nin another, former governor Ann Richards dates Bill. For 10 points, name this former FOX\ncartoon about Arlen, Texas."
      ],
      "answer": "King of the Hill"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) These places grew up after World War II on the \"Levittown\" model. These places were\nthe destination of \"white flight,\" and attempts to combine their (20 pts) ",
        "school systems with\nmajority-black districts in the 1970s led to \"busing\" programs. The automotive\ndependence of these places is criticized for contributing to (10 pts) ",
        "\"sprawl.\" For 10 points, name\nthese places to which middle-class Americans shifted after the 1950s, from which many people\ncommute to cities."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "suburbs",
        "suburb"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This movement's victory was secured at the Battle of Vertières (pr. VAIR-tee-air). This\nmovement was started by the \"houngan\" Dutty Boukman, and it was partially betrayed to\nCharles (20 pts) ",
        "Leclerc. Following this movement's success, its victors immediately split into\nfactions supporting either Henri (10 pts) ",
        "Christophe or Jean-Jacques Dessalines. For 10 points,\nname this successful slave rebellion which was initially led by Toussaint L'Ouverture (pr. TOOsahn ver-TOR)."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Haitian revolution",
        "slave revolt in Haiti"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) These items may have been named for the shipworkers on Hog Island who enjoyed them\nin the Philadelphia area. Another name for these items is attributed to Dominic Conti, who\ntook inspiration from viewing the (20 pts) ",
        "Fenian Ram on display in a museum. Less certain\norigins for this object’s names include the New England term (10 pts) ",
        "“grinder” and the New\nYork area “hero.” For 10 points, name this lunch food popularized by Italian-Americans and now\nserved as a “five-dollar footlong.”"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "subs",
        "sub",
        "hoagies",
        "hoagie"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man coined the name \"scissors crisis\" during the period of the New Economic\nPolicy. He also created the term \"degenerated workers state\" to summarize his views on\nwhat the (20 pts) ",
        "Soviet Union became following his deposition as head of the Red Army. He\nwas ultimately killed in (10 pts) ",
        "Mexico by Ramon Mercador. For 10 points, name this member of\nthe Left Opposition who was outmaneuvered by Joseph Stalin for leadership of the USSR."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Leon Trotsky",
        "Trotsky"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Frank Morris and the Anglin brothers left fake heads behind at this location in 1962.\nFrom 1969 to 1971, this location was occupied in a political protest by the Indians of All\nTribes. Burt (20 pts) ",
        "Lancaster played the title role in a film about Robert Stroud, the\n\"birdman\" of this place. Officially, no one ever (10 pts) ",
        "escaped from this place, assuming Morris\nand Anglin drowned before reaching Angel Island. For 10 points, name this former prison and\nisland off San Francisco."
      ],
      "answer": "Alcatraz"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) (TIEBREAKER EXAMPLE QUESTION) This king was the beneficiary of the original Act of Supremacy. He raised funds for the\nmiddle part of his reign by dissolving nearly all monasteries in his kingdom, with the\nassistance of his first administrator Thomas (20 pts) ",
        "Wolsey. This king was the father of\nEdward VI, (10 pts) ",
        "Mary I, and Elizabeth I. For 10 points, name this king whose attempt to divorce\nCatherine of Aragon triggered the English Reformation and his five subsequent marriages."
      ],
      "answer": "Henry VIII"
    }
  ]
}
